Lestoque, Albert; Papers ger059
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Albert (Leser) Lestoque Papers1862-1963
1899-1960
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Lestoque, Albert
ger059
15 cubic ft.
Records from legal battles and restitution claims of Albert (Leser) Lestoque and his two siblings, for family properties in the Plittersdorf section of Bonn, Germany. Also contains manuscripts and published versions of Lestoque’s writings, including the manuscripts from lecture engagements, and materials from organizations as Citizens for Victory, the International Committee for the Study of European Questions and the German American Writers’ Association (GAWA)
Biographical Sketch
Albert Lestoque was born Albert Leser on April 20, 1892 in Frankfurt am Main, Germany, the eldest son of well-to-do Jewish parents, Wilhelm and Helene Leser. Albert expressed an early interest in writing, however, since writing was not considered a proper profession at that time by either his immediate family or friends, Albert chose to follow in his father's footsteps and pursue a legal career. (In a letter to Will Schaber, dated February 13, 1939 [Albert Lestoque Papers], Albert stated that he turned to the study of law partly because of the fact that no other course of study attracted him, but also because of the practical possibilities a career in law could provide.)
Albert Leser pursued his legal studies at the Universities of Freiburg, Heidelberg, Bonn and finally Marburg, where he passed his doctorate exams in 1917 -- interrupted by service in the German army during World War I -- and passed the Assessor's exam in Berlin in the summer of 1920. During the next years, Albert practiced law, first as an Assessor and later as a prosecuting attorney, in Frankfurt am Main, Limburg and Wiesbaden until in 1933, because of his Jewish ancestry, he was deprived of his right to practice law in Germany. In the fall of 1934, realizing that a return to Germany was no longer possible for them, the Lesers established a second residence in Denmark. Finally, in 1937, Albert Leser, together with his wife and two young children, immigrated to the United States. Shortly after arriving in the U.S., Albert officially changed his name from Albert Leser to Albert Lestoque, a name he had used earlier in his writing career.
Albert Lestoque did not attempt to continue his legal career after emigrating to the U.S., but decided to pursue his writing career full-time. His only published novel, Menschen in Aktendeckeln, was published in German in 1939. After relocating to Denver, Colorado in 1941, Lestoque continued to write novels (none of which were published), prose and poetry, but he spent most of his time lecturing groups on topics such as the evils of National Socialism, crime and juvenile delinquency, democracy and peace. His most famous lecture, "American by Choice", first delivered on May 21, 1944, was reprinted numerous times.
After the end of World War II and the defeat of Germany, Albert Lestoque focused his energies almost entirely on trying to recover the family properties, which had been seized by the National Socialists in 1938. As the oldest of the three Leser siblings (brother Paul Leser and sister Maria Lingemann), Albert was the primary custodian of the family estate in the Plittersdorf section of Bonn, Germany. Albert's fight against the German government to regain his family's property and receive restitution (Wiedergutmachung) for himself, his siblings and his heirs, became the major focus of Albert's later years. Albert Lestoque died on November 19, 1960, shortly after the major restitution case against the German government (Deutsches Reich) was decided in his family's favor.
Chronology of Events:
1892 Born Albert Wilhelm Philipp Leser on April 20 in Frankfurt am Main, Germany to (Julius) Wilhelm and Helene Rikoff Leser, baptized as a member of the Reformed Evangelical Church.
1907 March 1907 confirmed as a member of the Deutsche evangelisch-reformierte Kirche in Frankfurt am Main.
1910 Completed his Abitur exams.
1911-1917 Studied law at the Universities of Freiburg, Heidelberg, Bonn and Marburg.
1917 Awarded his doctorate cum laude from the University of Marburg.
1915-1918 Served in the German army.
1920 Passed the Assessor exam.
1920-1926 Served as Assessor and later as prosecuting attorney in Frankfurt am Main, Neuwied and Königstein.
1924 Marriage to Gerda Maubach.
1926 Birth of daughter, Bettina.
1926-1931 Practiced law in Frankfurt am Main (Landgericht); also served as legal counsel to the printing firm of J. Maubach G.m.b.H. (company of his father-in-law).
1929 Birth of son, Walter.
1931-1932 Relocated to Switzerland; practiced law in Switzerland.
1932-1933 Practiced law in Cologne, Germany.
1933 May 5 deprived of the right to practice law in Germany by the Prussian Ministry of Justice.
1934 Fall established dual residency in Denmark.
1937 May 12 arrival with wife and two children in U.S.
1937 October 22 name legally changed from Albert Leser to Albert Lestoque (former pseudonym).
1938 March 30 Application for First Papers (Citizenship papers).
1939 Publication of novel, Menschen in Aktendeckeln.
1941 Divorced from Gerda; moved with son, Walter, to Denver, Colorado.
1944 December 15 became an American citizen.
1960 November 19 died in Bonn, Germany, after being hospitalized for a heart attack on November 11.
Scope and Contents
The collection reflects not only Lestoque's legal and literary careers, but also documents the story of a "German immigrant's family to establish roots in a new country, while fighting to protect their family heritage from the Third Reich and the tenacious battle through years of restitution claims". Approximately half of the materials in the collection deal with the legal battles and restitution claims of Albert (Leser) Lestoque and his two siblings, Paul Leser and Maria (Mira) Lingemann (née Leser), for family properties in the Plittersdorf section of Bonn, Germany. These materials include exhaustive correspondence files, family documents and property records dating from 1862, as well as numerous case files, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
In addition to the restitution files, the collection contains manuscripts and published versions of Lestoque's writings, including the manuscripts from Lestoque's lecture engagements, as well as materials collected by him pertaining to such organizations as Citizens for Victory, the International Committee for the Study of European Questions and the German American Writers' Association (GAWA).
Quote taken from a letter from Walter P. Leser to Marion Munzer, undated (after Dec. 15, 1982), Albert Lestoque Papers, M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged into 9 topical file series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Walter Leser, son Albert Lestoque, in 1982. M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, in 2006.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees.; Literature; Letters.; Correspondence.; Leser, Albert.; Lestoque, Albert.; Leser, Paul, 1899-,; German American Writers Association.; International Committee for the Study of European Questions.
- Biographical materials, documents, family documents and records, 1862-1960; 1; 41 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of two main sections: family documents and records, and biographical materials and documents of Albert (Leser) Lestoque. The family documents consist primarily of documents pertaining to the family estate known as Auf'm Rech located in the Plittersdorf section of Bonn, Germany. The records consist of land purchase records of various pieces of property primarily in Bonn, as well as records of furniture and art purchases for the property in Plittersdorf. Additional records pertaining to the property, as well as documents and materials pertaining to other family members are found in the Paul Leser Papers.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Records of Plittersdorf property land purchases & sales, 1862-1957 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 1)
  - Records of purchases of furniture, art objects, paintings for Leser family residence at Auf'm Rech, Plittersdorf, 1871-1883; 1.2
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1871 March 5 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 2)
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1871 April 25 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 3)
      (Collection Bernardus Lans zu Haarlem).
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1871 October 16 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 4)
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1871 October 17 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 5)
      (Sammlung von Romberg).
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1873 April 24-1873 April 25 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 6)
      (Collection W. H. De Heus de Nijenrode).
    - Purchase records, Auction (Sammlung Elinckhuyze), December 8-11, 1873 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 7)
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1876 September 25 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 8)
      (Sammlung von Schauroth).
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1881 September 19 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 9)
      (Sammlung de Francque).
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1881 September 22-1881 September 24 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 10)
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1881 October 24 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 11)
      (Sammlung Pickert).
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1882 March 27-1882 March 31 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 12)
      (Sammlung Herhold).
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1882 October 16 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 13)
      (Joh. Paul Hamburg).
    - Purchase records, Auction, 1883 May 7 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 14)
      (Collection L. Minard).
  - Property descriptions, Grundbuch Godesberg, 1938; 1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 15)
  - Property descriptions, Grundbuch Kessenich, 1936; 1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 16)
  - Property descriptions, Grundbuch Muffendorf, 1936 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 17)
  - Property descriptions, Grundbuch Rüngsdorf, 1938; 1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 18)
  - Property descriptions, Grundbuch Plittersdorf, 1925-1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 19-20)
  - Correspondence re: Plitterdorf property, 1928-1936 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 21)
  - Correspondence with Grundbuchamt Plittersdorf, 1959-1960 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 22)
  - Personal documents of Albert (Leser) Lestoque, 1892-1922 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 23)
  - Diary, 1909 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 24)
  - Student notebooks, ca. 1907-1910 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 25)
  - Polizeiliche Abmeldungen, 1931-1933 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 26)
  - Correspondence concerning immigration to Switzerland, 1931-1934 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 27)
  - Vertretungsverbot (ban on practicing law), 1933 May 5 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 28)
  - Plittersdorf mortgage, 1934 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 29)
  - Change of name from Leser to Lestoque, 1937 December 1 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 30)
  - Lloyds Underwriters London, insurance policies, 1937-1940 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 31)
  - U. S. Alien registration papers, 1937-1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 32)
  - Biographical statements, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 33)
  - Photograph of Albert Lestoque (1); photograph of Walter Lestoque, 1939 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 34)
  - Citizenship papers, 1942 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 35)
  - Correspondence concerning Albert Lestoque's blocked accounts, 1941-1949 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 36)
  - Schaber, Will. "Ein Staatsanwalt sucht das Recht". Introductory statement for Lestoque at German American Writers Association, 1939 April 5 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 37)
  - Clippings about Albert Lestoque, 1939-1942 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 38)
  - Clippings about Albert Lestoque, Denver society pages, 1944-1949 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 39)
  - Moving and storage records, 1951-1957 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 40)
  - Documents, correspondence re: death of Albert Lestoque, 1960 November 19 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials, documents, family document), Folder 41)
- Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- correspondence and materials, 1931-1935; 2; 25 file folders
  This series consists primarily of correspondence between Lestoque and officials or other members of the Akademischer Ruder-Club, a sports club in Bonn, Germany. The correspondence (1933-1935) deals with the denial of Lestoque's club membership rights due to his Jewish heritage.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - General correspondence, 1933-1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 1)
  - Der akademische Rudersport, 1932-1934 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 2)
  - Akademischer Ruderclub -- Clubnachrichten, 1931-1934 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 3)
  - A.R.C. Mitgliederverzeichnis, 1933 May 1 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 4)
  - Clippings re: student groups, 1933 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 5)
  - Bremme, Emil, 1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 6)
  - Cappenberg, Arnold, 1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 7)
  - Dyckerhoff, Karl J., 1933; 1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 8)
  - Ebhardt, Richard, 1933-1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 9)
  - Fassbinder, Engelbert, 1933-1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 10)
  - Garschina, Benno, 1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 11)
  - Geisseler, Hermann, 1933-1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 12)
  - Graham, William, 1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 13)
  - Haensel, Carl, 1933 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 14)
  - Holler, Otto, 1933 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 15)
  - Kohlermann, M., 1933-1934 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 16)
  - Rühl, Hans, 1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 17)
  - Simrock, Eugen, 1934 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 18)
  - Simrock, Karl, 1934 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 18)
  - Sonanini, A., 1934 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 19)
  - Steinstrauss, Erwin, 1933-1934 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 20)
  - Trendelenberg, Ernst, 1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 21)
  - Trube, Günter, 1933 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 22)
  - Uerdingen, August, 1933 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 23)
  - Vobis, Fritz, 1934-1935 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 24)
  - Windecker, Otto, 1934 (Box 2 (2-Akademischer Ruder-Club (A.R.C. Rhenus) -- corresp), Folder 25)
- Julius Lips materials, 1930-1932; 3; 35 file folders
  The Julius Lips materials consist of Albert Lestoque's files on the plagiarism case against Lips in which his brother, Paul Leser, was one of the primary accusers. These materials augment the larger collection of materials contained in the Paul Leser Papers.
  - Correspondence files, Undated; 3.1
    - Block, Martin, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 26)
    - Dessauer, Friedrich, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 27)
    - Deutsche Allgemeine Zeitung (Carl Haensel), 1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 28)
    - Honigsheim, Paul, 1930 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 29)
    - Imhoff, Kurt, 1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 30)
    - Kölnische Volkszeitung, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 31)
    - König, Herbert, 1931-1933 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 32)
    - Leser, Paul, 1926-1932 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 33)
    - Quadflieg, Eberhard, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 34)
    - Rhein-Mainische Volkszeitung, 1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 35)
    - Rhein-Westfälische Zeitung, 1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 36)
    - Sauer, Bind & Braun, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 37)
    - Sevenich, Maria, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 38)
    - Vatter, Ernst, 1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 40)
  - Case files -- Block vs. Lips, 1930 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 41)
  - Case files -- Foy Nachlass, 1930-1932 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 42-43)
  - Case files -- Quadflieg vs. Lips, 1930 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 44)
  - Lips Plagiarism case -- summarizations, Undated (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 45)
  - Lips, Julius. Einleitung in die Vergleichende Völkerkunde. 2 copies, with numerous underlinings and notes, Undated; 2 copies (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 46)
    With numerous underlinings and notes.
  - Lips Plagiarism case -- citations of plagiarized sections, Undated (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 47)
  - Statement by B. Ankermann, 1932 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 48)
  - Statement by Hermann Wolfgang Beyer, 1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 49)
  - Statements and summarization by Johannes Lehmann, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 50)
  - Statement by Paul Leser, Undated (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 51)
  - Statement by P. W. Schmidt and W. Koppers, 1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 52)
  - Statement by Bernhard Struck, 1930 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 53)
  - Statement by Hans zur Heyden, Undated (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 54)
  - Documents re: Lips' date and place of birth, doctoral degree, Undated (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 55)
  - Notes pertaining to the Lips case, Undated (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 56)
  - Newspaper clippings pertaining to the Lips case, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 57)
  - Case file -- Paul Leser vs. Prof. Menghin, 1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 58)
  - Case file -- Paul Leser vs. Dr. Röck, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 59)
  - Case file -- Ernst Vatter, Johannes Lehmann, Paul Leser vs. Prof. Thorbecke, 1930-1931 (Box 2 (3-Julius Lips materials), Folder 60)
- Writings of Albert Lestoque, 1909-1960; 4; 149 file folders
  Separated by genre and arranged alphabetically within genres.
  - Belletristic writings, Undated; 4.1; 73 file folders
    This series consists of both manuscripts and typescripts in German and in English. The largest portion of this section consists of texts of novels, including the handwritten manuscript of Lestoque's published novel, Menschen in Aktendeckeln, as well as versions of several unpublished novels. The poetry and short prose works are primarily written in German and date from 1909 to the 1930s, although a few examples in English date from his post-emigration time period.
    - Manuscripts and typescripts of novels and novellas, Undated; 4.1.1
      - Abdul Hamid am Zürichsee, undated (Box 2 (4.1.1-Manuscripts and typescripts of novels and novellas), Folder 61)
        Notes, primarily in German.
      - Abdul Hamid am Zürichsee, 1937-1939 (Box 2 (4.1.1-Manuscripts and typescripts of novels and novellas), Folder 62)
        Clippings, background materials.
      - Abdul Hamid am Zürichsee, 1933-1934 (Box 2 (4.1.1-Manuscripts and typescripts of novels and novellas), Folder 63)
        Materials for novel, correspondence.
      - The Amazing Mr. Dickson. Synopses, 1941 (Box 2 (4.1.1-Manuscripts and typescripts of novels and novellas), Folder 64)
      - The Amazing Mr. Dickson. German version, 1941; typescript (Box 2 (4.1.1-Manuscripts and typescripts of novels and novellas), Folder 65)
      - The Amazing Mr. Dickson. German version, dated 1960; typescript (Box 2 (4.1.1-Manuscripts and typescripts of novels and novellas), Folder 66)
      - A Gentlemen Racketeer. A Novel, 1942 (Box 2 (4.1.1-Manuscripts and typescripts of novels and novellas), Folder 67)
        English version of The Amazing Mr. Dickson. Typescript, plus additional handwritten pages.
    - The Amazing Mr. Dickson, new title: Oil, Love and Laughter. Bound typescript in English with additional pages inserted, 1945 (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 1)
    - Oil, Love and Laughter. Notes in English, Undated (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 2)
    - Oil, Love and Laughter. Background materials, clippings, 1944-1946 (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 3)
    - Oil, Love and Laughter. Background materials, clippings, 1950-1956 (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 4)
    - Anklage ab, Undated; typescript (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 5)
      Part I: "Die Verbrecher". 128pp. Part II: "Die Kriminal". 97pp.
    - Anklage ab, Undated; typescript (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 6)
    - Konrad Klüngelt (Das System). Novel based on the Julius Lips plagiarism case. Part I: "Ethnologisches und Pathologisches", Undated; typescript and manuscript (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 7)
    - Konrad Klüngelt. Background materials to planned chapters, Undated (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 8)
    - Die Lawine. Roman, 1942; typescript (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 9)
    - Avalanche (English translation of Die Lawine). Outline, loose pages, Undated (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 10)
    - Avalanche. A Novel, 1942; 351 pages (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 11)
    - Avalanche, Undated; 352+ pages (Box 3 (4-Writings of Albert Lestoque), Folder 12)